Okay, welcome to Nagarjuna course three.
We are going through
five years of Nagarjuna.
I always wanted to
translate his greatest book,
which is called "Wisdom",
or "Prajna".
So, I just decided that
during the Lam Rim times,
maybe I would give you guys some dessert.
And you know what happens
if you get too much dessert,
you get crazy.
So, we'd been filming
Nagarjuna number three.
It's going to take five
years to finish Nagarjuna.
And we're on the third year now.
And it's going well.
We are working on Choney
Lama's commentary.
Two good things happened yesterday.
You guys are going to
ask me what they were?
- [Students] What are they?
- Number one, we found the scan
of Choney Lama's commentary
that got lost 20 years ago
that came from his own monastery,
from Choney Monastery.
And so now I can actually check things.
And it was the only copy in the world.
And we can talk about that someday.
And secondly,
are you ready?
Peach Tree Cafe got all its permits
from the county
[audience applause]
after one and a half years of fighting.
I almost had a heart attack.
I don't know why they did
it, but God bless them.
So, I'm feeling good today.
I thought that since a
lot of you guys listening,
first of all, I'd like to thank you
for being the ACI volunteer team
and working all over the world
and making things happen for ACI.
I'm really, really grateful.
Say again?
Oh, we got Medicine Buddha volunteers too.
So, I was thinking what's a tasty dish
to serve up from Peach Tree Cafe
for ACI volunteers
and Medicine Buddha volunteers together.
What's something delicious
that I can give you?
Because that's what a
cafe owner has to do.
So, I thought a lot of
you are in the Gold Clubs.
A lot of you are helping
to support the project
to save the ancient books.
It will take about 700
years to save all the books
and it will take about, I don't know...
Just one book that we started this year,
is going to take 51 years to finish.
I don't know what's going to happen.
So, we've been working like that.
And I thought that since
a lot of you are involved
with ACIP...oh, ALL,
and how to save the books,
I thought today,
maybe it would be fun to start out
with describing to you how I use it.
So, I use this database
about 200-300 times every day
for the last 35 years.
And without it,
it'd be very difficult for me to teach.
What I'd like to do...
And we're sorry, our tech
is not too high today.
I'm holding one computer on my lap,
and I'm facing it to this other computer.
But I thought you'd like to see
what the database looks like,
because a lot of you
guys are raising money
for producing this database
and maybe you've never seen it in use.
And I sort of want to tie
it in to Nagarjuna today.
So, this is a special Nagarjuna class.
And during this version of Nagarjuna,
which is very, very difficult,
we are tying it into why
does Medicine Buddha work.
Why did the mantras work?
How does that tantra work?
And if you understand
how the mantras work,
how the practice works,
then it's going to work a lot better.
It's like a computer system.
If you understand how it works,
it can work better.
And if you don't understand how it works,
you could end up holding
a computer on your lap
to try to get the other screen to show.
So obviously, it's really useful
to know how something works.
So, if you understand
how the Medicine Buddha practice works,
then you can do it a lot better
and you can get better results from it.
We had a big discussion about it.
Some people were saying,
"Oh, it doesn't matter how it works.
Just teach them how to do it."
But I do believe that if
you know how it works,
it's more powerful.
If you're like an old grandma somewhere
and you just want to do mantras
and you don't want to know how they work,
that's okay.
I'm thinking about my mom, she's 95.
Maybe I can't explain to her
how the mantra works.
I can just tell her,
"Just do the mantras."
But if you understand how things work,
they work better.
So, here's the database.
Here's what it looks like.
Let's say I wanted to show
you something about Nagarjuna.
Of course, Nagarjuna's thing
is to explain emptiness.
Nagarjuna's most popular thing of all time
is to explain emptiness, of course.
And here's what the database looks like
on my computer.
Here's the different parts of the database
that I use everyday.
And I wanted to take you, I don't know,
let's go to the Tengyur.
This is 5,000 books that were
translated into Tibetan
and the translation took 700 years.
They finished it around the time
of Je Tsongkapa.
And it was 4,600 or 4,700 books.
And the first goal of ACIP...ALL
35 years ago,
was to input all their
ancient books from India,
which is all the sutras,
and all the commentaries,
and all the tantras.
The only problem was,
there was no copy in India of them.
They all got burned or destroyed.
So, the first job we had was to...
We actually contacted this
ancient, ancient monastery
that still had some blocks.
And we actually got into the library
and we had the blocks.
We had new pages printed from the blocks.
You're talking about 310,000 blocks.
310,000 blocks
to print all the things
from the Kangyur and Tengyur
from ancient India.
And we did it.
We finished. It took us about 10-12 years.
And we typed,
it's about 310,000 pages,
and we did it.
So, we have that what we can use.
Here's Tengyur.
These are all the commentaries
from ancient India.
And I wanted to...
Here's all the categories
of the Tengyur here.
For example, there's Perfection
of Wisdom, Middle Way,
there's Mind-Only, there's Abhidharma,
there's Vinaya,
there's Logic,
there's medicine,
there's architecture,
there's grammar.
There's books about how
to do practical things
like run a government.
There's even a book in here about
how to grade gemstones,
which was the most fun for me.
I wanted to show you these category,
the second one here,
which is called Vajrayana,
the Diamond Way.
And as you can see, it's almost...
Well, it's 78 different volumes,
which means 78,000 pages
of ancient commentaries
to the tantras.
The tantras are about 500,000 pages,
but here you've got about 78,000 pages
of commentary to them.
And these are divided.
By the way,
the arrangement of the
Vajrayana was secret,
and me and Venerable Jigme figured it out
using an ancient commentary that we found.
It was really a big, big deal
that after, I don't know,
this was carved 300-400 years ago,
somebody figured out
how they put the tantras
in the order that they are,
which is really awesome.
I don't know if you can see,
but here are the four classes of tantra.
There are four different levels of tantra.
For example, Medicine
Buddha is the fourth level
and highest level is called 'Anuttara'.
First level.
And let's go to Anuttara.
Here's, I don't know,
17 different categories
of different Anuttara Tantras.
For example, Chakrasamvara is here.
Kalachakra is here.
One part of Tara is here.
Perhaps the highest tantra
is called Guhyasamaja,
and this was the favorite of Je Tsongkapa.
And this is also the one that's used
for the tantric college,
where my teacher was the
assistant director in 1955.
If you go inside of the
Guhyasamaja secret books,
there's five huge categories
and hundreds of books.
The first category is
called KLU SGRUB LUGS
which means the system of Nagarjuna.
So, people ask me,
"Hey, did Nagarjuna know about tantra?"
Hey, the highest part
of the highest tantras is Nagarjuna.
And it's all dedicated to him.
It's 50 volumes
dedicated to Nagarjuna's interpretation
of the Diamond Way.
And he's the first person
mentioned in the Tengyur.
So, he's the greatest expert,
not only about emptiness,
but he's the greatest expert,
as you can see here, in
the secret teachings.
He's number one.
He was the highest teacher
and his system was recorded
and used in ancient India.
And there still exist a
couple of thousand pages
of explanation of his version
of the Guhyasamaja,
which is again Tsongkapa's favorite
tantra that he used himself.
So, there's the books from ancient India,
and the first grade emphasis
of the secret teachings,
of the highest class of
the secret teachings,
is Nagarjuna's system,
Nagarjuna's presentation,
which is very, very beautiful.
Now, suppose I'm working with the database
and I want to see...
Well, what did the Tibetans...
The Tibetans made a thousand
years of commentaries,
what did they say about
Nagarjuna's treatment
of the secret way,
the Diamond Way?
So then, in the database,
I would go to GSUNG 'BUM,
which means here's all the Tibetan books.
And I don't know,
we have something like
50,000 books finished.
And here you can say,
I clicked on BLO SBYONG,
and on the right,
you can see all the books.
Actually, it's all the shelves
of our digital library
that have BLO SBYONGs.
There's about 150 BLO SBYONGs there.
And by the way, it took 35
years of really hard work.
First of all, to find the books,
then to input the books.
And no one in history has cataloged them.
Nobody.
And we cataloged them.
It took about 30 years of work.
So, we don't talk about it much.
You guys probably never heard about it.
But it took thousands of hours of work
to put the library into order,
to put everything on shelves,
to say, "Oh, tantra is over here.
Middle Way is over here.
Abhidharma is over there."
And then to arrange all the shelves.
It took many, many, thousands of hours.
So, let's go to tantra.
Let's just see how did the
Tibetans deal with tantra?
So, it happens to be...
And by the way,
you can see all the categories here:
Vinaya, there is lineage trees,
there is history books,
Middle Way,
comparative philosophy, Abhidharma.
So, let's go to the tantra,
which is called RGYUD.
And on the right,
you can see all of the
different tantric systems.
There's 130.
Medicine Buddha is one.
And there's 129 others
that we have preserved.
So, you can see here,
for example, Manjushri,
White Manjushri, Chakrasamvara, Amitabha.
We have cataloged,
and we have saved 130
different schools of tantra.
So, Medicine Buddha is
just one school of tantra.
Then there's 129 others
that we have identified
and we have recovered.
So, if you look here...
Let's go to that
Nagarjuna's presentation
of the highest tantra
which is called Guhyasamaja
and it's right here.
Then you can see on the right here
are all the different categories
of the Guhyasamaja and commentaries:
how to move your mind on after you die,
how to do the guru
yoga, how to do retreat,
how to do the empowerment,
how to draw the mandala,
how to make the tormas,
how to do the mantras,
how to do the confession,
how to do the four powers
according to Guhyasamaja,
how to do the fire offering,
and many, many categories like that.
So, that's just Nagarjuna.
That's just Nagarjuna's tantra.
And let's check...
Let's see how many pages are there.
So, it's seven million bytes,
Seven million bytes.
Call it, I don't know...
If you transfer it into pages,
it's 7.5 megabytes just on Nagarjuna.
It's about 5,000 pages.
5,000 pages of Nagarjuna's explanation
of the secret teachings.
Why are we talking about all this?
Well, as maybe you noticed,
Nagarjuna made the ritual that we used
to take our Bodhisattva vows.
Without that ritual,
without some ritual
for the Bodhisattva vows,
you're not allowed to
study Medicine Buddha.
You have to take an empowerment
and then you have to take the vows,
at least a vow to try to be Bodhisattva.
You have to go through that ceremony.
And we used Nagarjuna's ceremony.
Now today we're going to
jump into the swimming pool
called Nagarjuna,
and it's extremely hard.
We're going to be jumping into
his teachings on emptiness.
- Geshe-la, what's it got
to do with Medicine Buddha?
- Well, here's the search
program for the database.
We invented this search program.
I thought you'd like to see how it works.
I'm going to search 5,000
books from ancient India.
I'm going to look for any presentation of
BYANG CHUB KYI SEMS, of Bodhichitta,
and I just used a part of
the name because it's faster.
And then I'm going to look
at it near his name, Naga.
Did Nagarjuna write
anything about Bodhichitta?
- Why, Geshe-la, why are
you off to Bodhichitta now?
- Because I'm irritated.
- Why are you irritated?
- Because I'm aggravated.
- Why you aggravated?
- I talked to somebody yesterday.
They said, "Oh, we went
on to Medicine Buddha,
"we don't need Lam Rim anymore.
"We're advanced now.
We don't have to do Lam Rim."
And I'm like, [growls] I got aggravated.
So the person who wrote
8,000 pages of commentary based on him
and some by him
on the highest teachings of tantra -
did he study Lam Rim?
Did he think Lam Rim was still important
or did he just go on to Medicine Buddha?
Well, here it is.
You can ask the database.
"Hey, database.
Sorry.
Did Nagarjuna think
Bodhichitta was important?"
And then you can look.
You going to search, I don't know,
a million pages in one and a half seconds.
Are you ready? Are you watching?
Here we go.
One, two, three, found!
Found it.
It took less than a second I guess.
And there it is.
KLU SGRUB means Nagarjuna.
And here's the book called
BYANG CHUB KYI SEMS BSKYED PA'I CHO GA
Yes.
He wrote a ritual
for taking the bodhisattva vows
and it's in the ancient books.
Did he write anything else?
Yeah.
He wrote this:
a commentary on how to get bodhichitta.
He wrote a commentary on
how to get bodhichitta.
Where is that commentary located?
In the tantras.
Okay?
Nagarjuna's commentary
on how to get bodhichitta
is tantric.
It's in the tantra.
I didn't say so.
They said so.
So, now you've got 8,000
pages of tantric commentaries
and root texts about
Nagarjuna's system on tantra.
Maybe he understands Medicine Buddha.
Maybe he thought it was important
to take your bodhisattva
vows as part of tantra.
He wrote the book!
He wrote the book, okay?
So I just wanted to impress on you guys,
there's a huge connection.
You've got to study Lam Rim
if you want to study tantra,
Medicine Buddha.
And especially the part of the Lam Rim
that deals with compassion and love,
and especially the part about emptiness.
You've got to understand emptiness,
or the mantra doesn't work.
You can sit and do mantras all day,
but if you don't understand
how something works,
it doesn't work.
It's weird.
You can say mantras, it's okay.
You get a little good karma
because of your motivation.
But if you go and fight your way through
Nagarjuna's presentation on emptiness,
then you're really going to
understand Medicine Buddha.
So we call this program
'The Emptiness of Medicine Buddha',
and let's jump into the
emptiness of Medicine Buddha.
And I say,
it's the only way to make
it work for you really well.
I'm excited to share it
with all of you volunteers,
because I think you're
the most serious people
in the whole world.
And I like serious people.
There's a lot of people that
if I say
let's fight our way through Nagarjuna's
most difficult book about emptiness,
because he understood tantra
and he knew it was necessary
for Medicine Buddha.
In fact, it's got 8,000 pages
about his understanding of tantra
in the database already.
Let's think through it.
So I trust you guys
won't get confused or go crazy.
We have to fight our way
deep through emptiness. In the monastery,
if the teacher can make you
confused about emptiness,
they think it's progress.
If you think you understand
emptiness after half an hour,
you're wrong.
It took me about 20 years or something.
So here we go.
We're going to go to
our actual text today.
This is our deep dive class number seven.
Here we go.
All right, uncle Tim,
are you ready with...
This chapter,
let's go to the chapter name.
By the way we're well
into the text already.
This is called Chapter 13,
and it's "An investigation of Factors".
Now, those sharp, sharp guys among you,
you should tell grandpa,
"Wait, we already did that in Chapter 1!".
Well, what was the name of Chapter 1?
An Investigation of
Conditions.
RKYEN BZHI, the four conditions.
Now, 12 chapters later,
he decides to cover factors?
Well, what's the difference between
a factor and a condition?
Let's go back.
Can you bring it up again?
Yeah. 'DU BYED means
things that make other things happen.
Oftentimes 'DU BYED
means secondary causes,
which is why I translated it as factors.
For example, what's the
main cause of a tree?
It's the seed.
That's called NYER LEN GYI RGYU.
That's called the immediate cause.
And then you have 'DU BYED
which means contributing factors
like water, sunlight, fertilizer.
What's BRTAG PA mean you guys?
This is the chapter 'Investigation'.
Oops.
How do you stay in Sanskrit?
- [Male student] Pariksha.
- Pariksha.
Pariksa,
looking all around the question.
'Pari', like periscope,
'iksha', which came into German as
'alga', which came into English as
E-Y-E,
that's why there's a
Y, in the English word
for your eyeball.
So each chapter of the 27 chapters
in Nagarjuna's most difficult
and most important work called...
- [Male student] Pariksha.
- No, his book.
- [Male student] Prajna.
- Just 'Wisdom'.
And that's so Nagarjuna.
He didn't say "A discussion
of the details of wisdom'.
Somebody asked him,
what's your book name?
He said "Wisdom".
- Yeah but what...
- Wisdom.
- But...
And that's so Nagarjuna.
He's a man of few words.
So we're going to investigate,
how does one thing cause another thing.
But this particular chapter
is not named
in an obvious way.
In this case factors means illusion.
So what's the connection
between one thing causing another thing
and the idea of an illusion,
'maya', maya, an illusion.
So really he should have
called this maya pariksha,
It's not really discussing the
different kinds of factors.
It did that already in the first chapter.
By Chapter 13,
he's talking about how
do causes and conditions,
how are they involved with illusion?
So here we go.
Put on your seatbelt.
And by the way,
he's not satisfied with
covering illusion. At the end,
he covers STONG NYID KYI STONG PA
STONG PA NYID KYI STONG PA
- [Female student] The
emptiness of living beings?
- The emptiness of emptiness.
So you guys this morning,
you have bad luck.
You got on a rocket ship.
We're going to talk about
the emptiness of emptiness
by the time we finish today.
And I'll keep coming back to
the Medicine Buddha practice,
and showing why,
if you understand emptiness,
your mantras will be more powerful
and your practice will be more...
and you'll just be super
Medicine Buddha guy.
Okay?
All right, here we go.
First verse, Mr. Tim.
,BCOM LDAN 'DAS KYIS CHOS GANG ZHIG
,SLU BA DE NI BRDZUN ZHES GSUNGS,
,'DU BYED THAMS CAD SLU BA'I CHOS,
,DES NA DE DAG BRDZUN PA YIN,
BCOM LDAN 'DAS KYIS CHOS GANG ZHIG
The Buddha said,
every single thing in the world
SLU BA - cheats you.
Everything in the world cheats you.
The mantras of Medicine
Buddha also cheat you.
What?
Then I raise a 'why?'
Why?
Because BRDZUN PA
They lie to you.
Everything in the world is cheating you.
Why?
Because they lie to you.
BRDZUN PA GSUNGS, said the Buddha.
Now, there's a very...
I'm just going to get you ready,
if you ever get to the monastery
and you're ever debating in a colloquial
Tibetan at 2000 words a second,
somebody might bring
up this favorite topic.
SANGS RGYAS KYIS BRDZUN GSUNGS
It says here BCOM LDAN
'DAS KYIS BRDZUN GSUNGS
The Buddha spoke lie.
The Buddha spoke "lies".
Okay.
- So the Buddha doesn't follow
the 10 good deeds, right?
- What do you mean?
- He broke number four.
- What's number four?
- He's lying.
The Buddha spoke lies.
And if you want to have a fun debate
with one of the 12 year
olds at the monastery,
this is good for like an
hour and a half or something.
[mimicking small child voice]
"Buddha spoke lies!"
Here's where he spoke lies.
In Nagarjuna, he spoke lies.
But what does it really mean?
He said all things which
have causes are lying to you.
So he just mentioned the word lie,
he didn't speak a lie.
He spoke "lies",
but he didn't say a lie.
Got it?
It's a joke.
All right.
If you're ever debating
with the 12 year olds,
you can note it.
'DU BYED THAMS CAD SLU BA'I CHOS.
Everything that has a cause,
or everything that is a cause,
is lying to you.
Therefore...
Sorry.
Everything that has a
cause is cheating you,
therefore they are liars, BRDZUN PA
They are liars.
This is how Nagarjuna starts the chapter.
And that's why we had Tim and Grandpa
in the picture at the
beginning of the class.
And the idea is that,
I don't know,
the employee is cheating
the employer, I guess.
And he got caught.
So the idea is
the employee is cheating the employer,
and therefore he will have to
lie to the employer.
So there's a connection
between cheating and lying.
He stole the money, which is cheating.
And now he's going to
have to lie about it,
to keep the money.
All right, so just get in that mood.
We're talking about illusion.
We're talking about somebody lying to you.
All right, let's go to
the next verse, Tim.
,GAL TE SLU CHOS GANG YIN PA,
,DE BRDZUN DE LA CI ZHIG SLU,
,BCOM LDAN 'DAS KYIS DE GSUNGS PA,
,STONG NYID YONGS SU BSTAN PA YIN,
Look, okay I agree.
So suppose everything's cheating me.
DE BRDZUN DE LA CI ZHIG SLU
Then what's it lying about?
How do things, including
Medicine Buddha practice
and including Medicine Buddha mantra,
how are they lying to me?
How are they lying to me?
BCOM LDAN 'DAS KYIS DE GSUNGS PA
Look, he said they are lying to you.
And that got him into the subject
of STONG NYID - emptiness.
- Wow, what did he mean?
- Well, the honesty of
that employee's transaction
don't exist.
He's cheating the company.
How much honesty is in his transaction?
How much honesty is going on
at that desk at that moment?
Zero.
And that's called emptiness. Got it?
When somebody lies to you,
there's no reality there.
Then the situation is empty of reality.
When someone cheats you, they lie to you.
When they lie to you,
the truth is gone.
And that's a kind of emptiness.
If it's not real, it's empty.
Buddha said things that cheat you,
lie to you.
Everything around you is cheating you.
Everything around you, including
Medicine Buddha mantras,
is lying to you.
And therefore it's all empty.
There's no truth there.
Nothing's real.
Got it?
All right, then...
I don't know...
I was trying to find
a picture about lying,
here it is.
It's a Gucci bag
that you buy in Thailand on the street
for $2.
There's a place in,
oh no, it's in Bejing,
there's a special market.
My friend went crazy,
my friend from Israel,
he went to this market.
He bought like 30 Gucci
bags for all his relatives.
And they're each like a dollar.
You pick them up and the
handle falls off them,
stuff like that.
So it looks like a Gucci bag,
but it's a fake Gucci bag.
And the Buddha said
everything around you is like that,
everything's lying to you.
Let's go to the next verse.
Oh, sorry.
I'm going to throw a quotation
and it's not in your...
So when did the Buddha talk about lying?
Supposedly the Buddha
has talked about lying.
So can you show me the quotation?
And Choney Lama takes the challenge
and he says, "I'll show you the quote.
I got a quotation where
Buddha talked about it"
And it's called MA DROS PAS ZHUS PA LAS
MA DROS PA means a special
lake that will never dry out.
DROS PA means dry out.
MA DROS PA means can never dry out.
Anavatapta
in Sanskrit, Anavatapta,
which means, sometimes
it's called not warm,
but there's a naga living in the lake.
His name is MA DROS PA - Anavatapta.
Sometimes they call it not warm or warm.
And he's having a conversation
with Lord Buddha in this sutra.
It's the sutra of the naga in the lake.
And he says, Buddha says,
,GANG ZHIG RKYEN LAS SKYES PA DE MA SKYES,
,DE LA SKYE BA'I RANG BZHIN YOD MA YIN,
Anything that comes from conditions...
There's our conditions.
Anything that comes from
causes and conditions
like seeds or water or fertilizer,
anything that's born from water and seeds,
is never born.
Anything that is born from
water and seeds is not born.
Buddha said, "It's all fake.
It's all a lie."
DE LA SKYE BA'I RANG BZHIN YOD MA YIN
There's no nature of being born there.
Nothing's being born. There's no
the slightest bit of being born there.
RKYEN LA RAG LAS GANG DE STONG BAR BSHAD
I tell you, anything that's
mixed up with causes is empty.
It's a lie.
The truth is gone.
GANG ZHIG STONG NYID SHES DE BAG YOD YIN
Anybody who really understands that
can do stuff well,
like Medicine Buddha
practice, BAG YOD YIN.
You know, BAG YOD means like a new born...
like a new wed woman,
something like that.
It means they are skillful.
They are living in the right way.
Anyone who understands emptiness
is doing a good Medicine Buddha practice.
Who said that?
The Buddha said that.
Why?
Because they understand
the illusion there.
They understand that
there's emptiness there.
And that's where the
Buddha described lies.
Anything that has a cause is lying to you.
If you get it,
then you can live a good life.
You can have a good practice.
Got it?
All right, I went and found it for you.
I'll put it in the
translation when I finish it.
By the way, translation
is already 400 pages,
and it's tough.
It's really tough.
We're going through it at
about 110 miles an hour.
It should take 20 years or something.
All right, here we go.
Next verse.
It's really a verse and a half by the way.
What did I say is tricky
about reading Nagarjuna?
What did I say
could trip you up?
- [Male student] (indiscernible)
- Yeah.
Sometimes it sprinkles in
the other guy's comments,
and he doesn't warn you.
There's no warning.
And you need Choney Lama to tell you,
"No, no, this is not Nagarjuna.
This is the other guy."
So here's the other guy;
,DNGOS RNAMS NGO BO NYID MED DE,
,GZHAN DU 'GYUR BA SNANG PHYIR RO,
,DNGOS PO NGO BO NYID MED MED,
,GANG PHYIR DNGOS RNAMS STONG PA NYID,
,GAL TE NGO BO NYID MED NA,
,GZHAN DU 'GYUR BA GANG GI YIN,
Here's the other guy.
DNGOS RNAMS NGO BO NYID MED DE
If stuff doesn't have a
true nature of its own,
if things don't have a
true nature of their own,
Nagarjuna says they don't, by the way,
He says,
if things don't have a
true nature of their own,
GZHAN DU 'GYUR BA SNANG PHYIR RO
then why do they change?
And by the way,
the example is going
to be when you use milk
to make yogurt.
In India,
the way you make yogurt in the market is
you get a bowl of hot milk,
you put in the yeast from the last yogurt,
and then you're hang it up in your shop.
And the flies cover it for the whole day.
You can't even see the white color.
It's all black.
And then they serve it the next day.
When I got back from India,
the doctor told me I had
17 kinds of parasites.
So anyway,
the milk transforms into yogurt.
Can you tell the difference
between the yogurt and the milk?
Yeah, it's different.
It tastes different.
It's sticky, right?
Then the other guy says
an interesting thing.
He says, look, if things that have causes
have no nature of their own,
then how can they change?
If the milk didn't have an identity,
then how did it drop that
identity and become a yogurt?
Got it?
So according to you, Nagarjuna,
if everything's empty,
and it has no nature of its own,
then milk can never change.
Because it has to have a nature to change.
It has to be something
before it can change into something else.
If it's not something in the first place,
how can it become yogurt?
GZHAN DU 'GYUR BA SNANG PHYIR RO
We can see things change.
DNGOS PO NGO BO NYID MED MED
Therefore, it's not true
that nothing has any nature of it's own.
MED MED
It's not true that things have no nature.
GANG PHYIR DNGOS RNAMS STONG PA NYID
Okay, say things are empty.
GAL TE NGO BO NYID MED NA
If the milk doesn't have
a nature of being milk,
GZHAN DU 'GYUR BA GANG GI YIN
well, how can it become yogurt?
How can it drop its former identity
and take on a new identity
if it never had an identity?
This is the other guy
talking to Nagarjuna.
And if you don't know it's the
other guy, you're in trouble.
And I found a picture that I like:
it's leaves, green and
different colored leaves.
It's...
I don't know.
It's springtime here.
We're thinking about leaves and...
If the leaf wasn't green,
how could it turn yellow?
Got it?
If the leaf wasn't green,
how could it turn yellow?
- Nagarjuna,
you said nothing has
any nature of its own.
- Okay, I did.
- So leaves aren't green?
- What's that got to do with anything?
- Well, if they're not green,
how can they turn yellow?
Then how can you say 'turn'?
They must be green.
Those green leaves are green.
They have a nature.
They're green.
If they didn't have a nature,
they couldn't become yellow.
It makes sense right?
Got it?
Yes, you're correct.
All right, here we go.
Next verse,
,GAL TE NGO BO NYID YOD NA,
,CI LTA BUR NA GZHAN DU 'GYUR,
And Nagarjuna's answer is, "No.
If things did have a nature,
how could they change?"
The other guy said,
if green leaves aren't green,
how can they turn to yellow?
And then Nagarjuna says,
if green leaves were green,
they couldn't turn to yellow.
Your argument defeats yourself.
If green leaves are green,
they can't become yellow leaves.
They're green.
You can't call it yellow
a green leaf. Come on.
If a green leaf was really green,
it couldn't become yellow.
So don't give me this stupid example that,
because things change,
they must have had some nature
because you couldn't say they changed
if they didn't have a
nature in the first place
to change from.
Got it?
You okay?
Just keep nodding.
You guys at home just keep nodding.
CI LTA BUR NA GZHAN DU 'GYUR
So he uses the argument
back to the other guy.
If green leaves are green,
then they can't become yellow leaves,
because they're green leaves.
Got it?
He uses the same argument back to the guy.
Here's the picture.
This picture was easy to find.
Okay, if green leaves are green,
they can never be yellow.
Duh.
If green leaves had a nature
of being green,
they could never become yellow leaves.
The other guy said,
if they don't have a
nature of being green,
how can you observe a change in them
if they drop that nature
and become yellow?
Got it?
So they must have had a nature.
All right, now,
Choney Lama uses a very
beautiful word here
and I want to use it
for our Sanskrit lesson.
So every Nagarjuna class we have,
we're going to do a mini Sanskrit lesson.
So you've got to learn a
little bit of Sanskrit.
Don't worry, it won't hurt you.
It's like 15 words for the whole course.
But since you have to
speak in Sanskrit later,
after the Medicine Buddha practice,
which has no nature,
makes you a Medicine Buddha,
you're going to have to speak Sanskrit.
So you might as well
go get used to it now.
It's like you're going to Guadalajara,
you might as well learn about five words.
It makes the taxi drivers so happy.
All right.
So here we go.
You got that one from me, you guys?
This is our little Sanskrit lesson.
This is a word called...
By the way I misspelled it there, Tim,
is it too late to fix it?
Prakirti, it should be K-I-R.
This is an old mistake
that everyone else makes.
Prakirti.
And those of you may have heard it.
You've probably heard this 'prakirti',
it's a very famous word
in Hindu yoga schools.
It's a very famous idea.
In Tibetan it's called GSHIS LUGS
GSHIS LUGS
Say GSHIS LUGS
- [Class in unison] GSHIS LUGS
- [GMR] GSHIS LUGS
And that GSHIS is a very unusual word
that means 'the primordial
nature' or something.
GSHIS
And it happens to be used
in a famous expression
BKRA SHIS BDE LEGS
which means are you having
a good primordial nature?
[GMR laughs]
And that's how you say "hi" in Tibetan.
You say BKRA SHIS BDE LEGS
which means wonderful
primordial shining nature.
BKRA SHIS BDE LEGS
When you say "thank you" in Tibetan,
what's it mean?
THUGS RJE CHE
- [Female student] (indiscernible)
- You're great heart.
You're great holy heart.
It's how you say "thank you".
And how you say "good morning"
is "shining primordial nature
of happiness and goodness".
Which used to be the expression for
Happy New Year.
And then it became so common
that people started using
it for good morning.
Alright.
Prakirti comes from pra-,
the prefix letter pra-,
and then kirti.
And by the way people say
"prakriti" and it's wrong.
The pronunciation is wrong.
Prakrit, people say prakrit,
and that's like saying,
it's like your German friends who say
"I went and bought cheap (Jeep)
and drove it home."
It's just a mistake of pronunciation.
All right, so pra- means forward,
or very much.
√kṛ is the verbal root that means
to make or to do.
We spoke about pra- many times.
√kṛ we spoke about,
it's found in 'cereal',
'create' and 'karma'.
And the C in cereal used to be K.
It changed around the time of Shakespeare.
And then -ta makes it a past tense.
And I think it came into English
with E-D:
made it,
or I created - '-ed', '-ted'.
So prakirti means that which
was made from the beginning.
And it means the original
nature of an object.
In Sankhya philosophy,
in ancient Hindu yoga philosophy,
they will juxtapose two things.
Ms. Kasica:
prakirti and...
- [Ms. Kasica] Parusha
- Parusha
Prakirti and parusha
So 'parusha' means the Person.
And it means God,
the Person, capital P,
who made everything.
And then prakirti is the nature
which was made by the God.
So in Hinduism, especially in
the ancient yoga philosophy
prakirti is nature
and parusha is the creator.
But in Buddhism,
prakirti means the nature,
which things can not have.
The original nature,
green leaf.
Green is in the leaf, like that.
So try to remember that.
That's called GSHIS LUGS.
And Choney Lama is very
skillful to use the word.
So now, today you learned a new word:
prakirti, that which was
made in the beginning.
Pra- kirti and the nature of things.
When Michael was made by his parents,
was he made with a nature
built in from the factory?
Did he have a nature prakirti in him
from the factory?
From my mom factory.
Alright, here we go.
Next subject.
,DE NYID LA NI GZHAN 'GYUR MED,
,GZHAN NYID LA YANG YOD MA YIN,
,GANG PHYIR GZHON NU MI RGA STE,
,GANG PHYIR RGAS PA'ANG MI RGA'O,
Now Nagarjuna, he's got...
He just jumps on you.
- Hey, you guys're talking
about change, right?
Green leaf changes yellow, right?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Does that have a nature?
Does the changing have a nature?
Got it?
Folks forget the leaf now.
Did the green leaf have a nature?
We say no. They say yes.
They say it had to have a
nature because it changed.
If it didn't have an identity,
how could it take on a new
identity of being yellow?
How could milk change,
drop its old identity and become yogurt
if it didn't have an
identity in the first place.
Now we say, "By the way,
you guys want to talk about
the emptiness of change?"
When the milk becomes yogurt,
when the leaf turns to yellow,
what's the emptiness of that?
DE NYID LA NI GZHAN 'GYUR MED
If things have a primordial
nature, prakirti,
GZHAN 'GYUR MED
they cannot change to something else.
GZHAN NYID LA YANG YOD MA YIN
If things are self-existently separate,
they can't have a nature
if things are self-existently
separate or other.
Is the yellow leaf different
from the green leaf?
Yeah, it's yellow.
Is the yogurt different from the milk?
Yeah.
Is that difference self-existent?
GANG PHYIR GZHON NU MI RGA STE
Young people don't get old,
and old people don't get old either.
That's Nagarjuna.
Young people don't get old,
and old people don't get old either.
Now let's do the second
one because it's easier.
- Do old people get old?
- No, they're already old.
- Okay, we got that one finished.
Now the big question is,
do young people get old?
- No, because they're young people.
- Okay, listen.
Do young people get old?
- No.
- Why?
- They're young.
Yeah, it's separate.
It's totally separate.
- Do old people get old?
- No, they are already old.
- Do young people get old?
- No, they're young.
- Got it?
- Quit fooling around with the words!
- I'm not fooling around with words.
I'm trying to demonstrate to you
that words are messed up already
and you don't notice it.
- Young got old.
- What are you talking about?
Young old, an old young person?
What do you mean?
- Something's wrong.
The mantra cured the cancer.
Yhe Medicine Buddha
mantra cured the cancer.
- What's the connection?
- The mantra never touched the cancer.
How can it cure the cancer?
Are they separate or not?
,GAL TE DE NYID GZHAN 'GYUR NA,
,'O MA NYID NI ZHOR 'GYUR RO,
How does milk become ZHO?
ZHO means yogurt.
If you ever get hungry ask for some ZHO
but say low tone ZHO.
Don't say SHO
SHO means dice
and it means you want to lose some money.
Don't say, I'm hungry,
I need some SHO - ZHO -  ZHO.
,O MA NYID NI ZHOR 'GYUR RO,
,'O MA LAS GZHAN GANG ZHIG NI,
,ZHO YI DNGOS PO YIN PAR 'GYUR,
Is the milk separate
from the yogurt or not?
Are they separate things?
Yes or no?
I'm not tricking you.
Here's Nagarjuna,
typical Nagarjuna,
"Hey I'm not tricking you.
Just answer the question."
Is the milk the yogurt?
- [Female student] No.
- Are they separate?
- [Female students] Yes.
- Do they ever touch?
Cannot.
Why?
The milk was yesterday.
The yogurt is today.
They can't overlap.
If they touch at any point,
then yesterday is today.
It's not possible.
Milk cannot turn into yogurt.
Something weird is going on.
Medicine Buddha mantra cannot cure cancer,
but it does.
And that's how we get yogurt, right?
How many times you ate yogurt?
There must be something
there. All right, next.
I have a picture of a
grandma and granddaughter.
The granddaughter is not old,
getting old.
And the grandma's not getting old,
because the grandma already got old.
And the daughter's young.
All right, go figure it out.
Next one.
Huh, this class is going to...
Let's see.
Now, according to Choney Lama,
who's guiding us,
and by the way
we haven't gone through the commentary.
Commentary would take about
20 years to teach, really.
And it's beautiful.
But he warns us.
Choney Lama says,
STONG NYID RANG BZHIN GYIS
YOD PA'I SGRUB BYED DGAG PA'O
I'm going to prove to you that emptiness
doesn't have a nature of it's own.
I'm going to prove to you
the emptiness is empty.
And that's his big thing.
The next verse is one of
the most famous verses
of this whole book.
And it's kind of an honor
that we have all our Medicine Buddha
and ACI volunteers here today
because we hit maybe the most,
well, second most famous
verse from this whole book.
And it's just cool that you're here,
because in five years,
it's only going to happen once.
So here we go.
,GAL TE STONG MIN CUNG ZAD YOD,
,STONG PA CUNG ZAD YOD PAR 'GYUR,
,MI STONG CUNG ZAD YOD MIN NA,
,STONG PA YOD PAR GA LA 'GYUR,
GAL TE STONG MIN CUNG ZAD YOD
If there's anything that's not empty,
if there's the slightest
thing which is not empty,
STONG PA CUNG ZAD YOD PAR 'GYUR
you could have the
slightest thing which isn't.
If there's the slightest
thing which isn't empty,
then you can have the
slightest bit of emptiness.
MI STONG CUNG ZAD YOD MIN NA
If there isn't the slightest
thing which is not empty,
STONG PA YOD PAR GA LA 'GYUR
how could you have emptiness?
You need the opposite to define a thing.
If there's no such thing
as not being empty,
how are you going to recognize emptiness?
You recognize things by
comparison to other things.
How do you know something's blue
if it's not yellow?
If blue was around you all the time,
if everything in your room was blue
you wouldn't see the blue.
I mean, you'd be looking at it,
but you wouldn't see it.
So this is a very famous proof
that emptiness has its own emptiness.
Now, how is that?
Let's look at this picture.
This is a glass of water,
which is completely full.
It's definitely not empty,
but there would have to
be some part of non-empty,
if the emptiness came from its own side.
If emptiness came from its own side,
there would have to be part
which is not empty.
Therefore, that last statement was...
Who was talking?
Sounds like the other guy.
Okay, Nagarjuna,
So must be some stuff...
If things don't have an
identity of their own,
then the only way you're
going to recognize it
is by looking at the opposite.
Therefore, there must be
some things in the universe
that aren't empty,
and you can compare them to
the things that are empty,
and you can tell they're empty.
Otherwise, how could you ever see -
if emptiness didn't have its own nature?
If it were only empty by comparison.
Okay, here we go.
If you're not confused yet,
we'll work on it.
Let's go to the next verse.
,RGYAL BA RNAMS KYIS STONG PA NYID,
,LTA KUN NGES PAR 'BYUNG BAR GSUNGS,
,GANG DAG STONG PA NYID LTA BA,
,DE DAG BSGRUB TU MED PAR GSUNGS,
This is a very subtle verse,
it takes a lot of work.
I'll introduce it to you.
And what my teacher said was
you have to cook it.
Rebecca used to sit with my teacher.
"You cook it."
We said, "No, no, we don't
understand anything."
"Cook it, God damn, cook it.
I'm going home."
I should try that.
RGYAL BA RNAMS KYIS STONG PA NYID
The victors stated about emptiness,
LTA KUN NGES PAR 'BYUNG
This NGES 'BYUNG
- first principle path -
is renunciation.
But it also means to rip something out,
to rip something,
NGES PAR 'BYUNG
pull it out.
Pull yourself out of the home life
is called renunciation.
But here,
the Buddha said that emptiness rips out
LTA KUN, LOG LTA - wrong views.
They said if you get emptiness,
it will renunciate your wrong views.
Pull them out of the house,
get out. This house [points to his head].
GANG DAG STONG PA NYID LTA BA
This is very subtle.
Whosoever sees emptiness.
Whosoever thinks they see emptiness
being from its own side.
That's the trick.
Whosoever sees emptiness,
DE DAG BSGRUB TU MED PAR GSUNGS
This BSGRUB means fixable,
repairable. MED
What's the biggest mistake
you can make in life?
If you think that emptiness
has its own nature.
Then you are hopeless.
Truly hopeless.
Who said that? GSUNGS - the Buddha.
If you think the mantra is going to work
from it's own side,
you are hopeless.
Totally hopeless.
It's better you didn't hear the mantra.
If you're going to grab onto the mantra
as working from its own side,
and you don't need to save life
for the mantra to work...
Okay?
If you think the mantra is going to work
from its own side
without saving life, then
you're going around saying
mantras without saving life -
good luck.
You're hopeless.
Who said that?
Buddha.
BSGRUB TU MED PAR here means,
you are broken and no one can fix you.
Why?
Because you're using the dharma already,
but you're using it wrong.
So you're the worst kind of broken.
And I can't do anything for you.
I can't fix you.
Who said that?
Buddha said that.
Pretty heavy.
So that finishes our class today.
Again, it's a special
treat class suffering for
those of you who have
been helping so much.
And I know I helped my Lama for 30 years.
I washed dishes for 30 years.
Me and Elly found a picture of us
shoveling snow outside,
when it used to snow
before the global warming.
That was the whole day. It was like that.
So I got to tell you
that being a volunteer is the coolest,
smartest thing you can do.
Really, honestly, I'm not just selfish.
And I did it for 30 years.
And I look back at those times,
some of my friends from Princeton,
they used to say,
"That guy is taking advantage of you,
"you're working all day for free.
"You could be a big lawyer
"or you could be a big
government official."
They're all dead now.
Or they got cancer
and they write me letters
every day, all day.
"Help me, help me,
"I don't know what to do,
teach me something."
These guys told me, when
I went to my teacher,
you're a fool to spend all day
volunteering for your teacher.
But I look back at those days...
I look back at those days
and I was really, really happy.
Those were the happiest days of my life.
So you are very smart to be a volunteer.
And keep going.
And you'll look back at these days
and you'll say,
oh, that was the best time of my life.
All right. See you later.